<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-20T21:18:14+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Mapping how krill larvae get from spawning grounds to nurseries along the Antarctic Peninsula</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/meps-connectivity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping how krill larvae get from spawning grounds to nurseries along the Antarctic Peninsula"/><published>2026-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/meps-connectivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/meps-connectivity/"><![CDATA[<p>Our paper <strong>“Modeled connectivity of Antarctic krill spawning and nursery grounds along the Western Antarctic Peninsula”</strong> is out today in <em>Marine Ecology Progress Series</em>.</p> <blockquote> <p>Sylvester, Z.T., Dinniman, M.S., Thorpe, S.E., Bernard, K.S., Brooks, C.M. (2026). Modeled connectivity of Antarctic krill spawning and nursery grounds along the Western Antarctic Peninsula. <em>Marine Ecology Progress Series</em>, 779, meps15059. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3354/meps15059">https://doi.org/10.3354/meps15059</a></p> </blockquote> <p>Our goal was to model connectivity between spawning and nursery grounds of Antarctic krill and try to answer the question: <strong>What areas are important for ontogenetic habitat partitioning in early life stages of krill and how does connectivity between regions influence broader population dynamics</strong></p> <hr/> <h3 id="why-connectivity-matters">Why connectivity matters</h3> <p>Antarctic krill are the foundation of the Southern Ocean food web, and their populations depend on successful recruitment, meaning larvae surviving long enough to join the adult population. But between spawning and recruitment lies a gauntlet: eggs sink, embryos develop through a descent–ascent cycle, and the resulting larvae are at the mercy of ocean currents for months.</p> <p>The western Antarctic Peninsula (wAP) is one of the most important regions for krill globally, but we’ve had surprisingly little mechanistic understanding of how larvae move between spawning areas and the nursery grounds where they develop. Are nursery grounds self-sustaining, or do they depend on larval supply from elsewhere? How reliable are those supply pathways from year to year? And what happens when the winds change?</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/meps-reference-map-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/meps-reference-map-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/meps-reference-map-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/meps-reference-map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Reference Map" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Nursery grounds: BS: Bransfield Strait; GS: Gerlache Strait; GP: Grandidier Passage; MB: Marguerite Bay (see Table S2 for coordinates). Geographic features are labeled (Mrg. Trough: Marguerite Trough). </div> <hr/> <h3 id="what-we-did">What we did</h3> <p>We used a circumpolar Southern Ocean ROMS (Regional Ocean Modeling System) configuration with a 5 km grid, 32 vertical layers, and ERA5 atmospheric forcing to simulate ocean circulation across the entire continental shelf, including under ice shelves, for three austral summers (2016–2019).</p> <p>Within this model, we released Lagrangian drifters on a 25×25 km grid across the Southern Ocean to simulate larval krill transport. These aren’t passive particles. They follow a vertical behavior model that represents the krill life cycle: eggs descend for roughly 5 days and are removed if they reach the seafloor before hatching. Survivors ascend through larval stages, and after about 60 days adopt a diel vertical migration pattern. Their movement is driven by ocean and sea ice velocities, with the balance depending on sea ice concentration and particle depth.</p> <p>This biological detail is crucial. Where a larva sits in the water column determines which currents carry it, and that changes over the course of development.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/ascent-descent-withtext-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/ascent-descent-withtext-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/ascent-descent-withtext-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/ascent-descent-withtext.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Lagrangian drifter simulation design" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Lagrangian drifter simulation design: The Primary movement of particles is determined by ocean and sea ice velocities depending on sea ice concentrations and particle depth. Additional vertical behavior is determined by the life stage representing how krill larvae move through the water column. This detail is crucial for understanding how they interact with physical ocean properties and the habitat they reach during development. </div> <hr/> <h3 id="key-findings-nursery-by-nursery">Key findings: Nursery by nursery</h3> <p>We focused on the wAP, identifying four known nursery grounds: Bransfield Strait (BS), Gerlache Strait, Grandidier Passage, and Marguerite Bay (MB). By tracking which simulated larvae spent more than 21 days in each nursery region during their first 6 months of life, we could trace back to where those larvae were spawned and map the connectivity between spawning and nursery habitat.</p> <h4 id="bransfield-strait">Bransfield Strait</h4> <p>The Bransfield Strait functions as both a spawning ground and a nursery ground. The vast majority of larvae that used BS as a nursery were spawned within it. Self-retention dominates. But the external supply pathways are what make this system interesting, because they shift dramatically from year to year depending on the winds.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/BS_migration_tracks_dual_panel_h_dvm_2016-2018_revised-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/BS_migration_tracks_dual_panel_h_dvm_2016-2018_revised-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/BS_migration_tracks_dual_panel_h_dvm_2016-2018_revised-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/BS_migration_tracks_dual_panel_h_dvm_2016-2018_revised.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Lagrangian drifter simulation design" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Larval krill trajectories for the Bransﬁeld Strait nursery ground (BS-NG) across 3 consecutive summers (2016–2019), showing particle trajectories (A) into BS-NG for larvae not spawned locally and (B) particles exiting from BS-NG. Pathways are colored by simulation start year: 2016 (blue), 2017 (magenta), and 2018 (gold). Background shading represents seaﬂoor bathymetry (IBCSO v.2) </div> <p>The typical pattern is for larvae to be advected northeast along the continental shelf and into the Bransfield Strait. But local wind fields can enhance or completely redirect these inflows. In February 2017, strong northerlies near Boyd Strait created on-shelf Ekman transport that drew larvae in from a different direction entirely. In February 2019, weaker westerlies at the tip of the Peninsula facilitated transport from the Weddell Sea instead.</p> <p>Same nursery ground, same model, same biology, but the wind field determined <em>which external larvae got there and where they came from</em>.</p> <p>Larvae that left the Bransfield Strait were mainly advected north toward the South Scotia Ridge. But a subset was also carried south along the coastal current and into the two middle nursery grounds, the Gerlache Strait and Grandidier Passage. This makes BS not just a nursery in its own right, but a potential upstream source for nursery habitat further down the Peninsula.</p> <h4 id="gerlache-strait-and-grandidier-passage-secondary-nurseries">Gerlache Strait and Grandidier Passage: secondary nurseries</h4> <p>The two middle nursery grounds acted as secondary nursery habitats, receiving larvae from both local spawning and from advection out of the Bransfield Strait. Their shallower bathymetry meant shorter retention times compared to the deeper basins at either end of the Peninsula.</p> <h4 id="marguerite-bay-isolated-and-self-sustaining">Marguerite Bay: isolated and self-sustaining</h4> <p>Marguerite Bay stood out as fundamentally different from the northern nursery grounds. Like BS, it functions as both a spawning and nursery ground, with the majority of larvae that used MB as a nursery having been spawned within or near it. But unlike BS, Marguerite Bay’s external supply came almost entirely from the south, via the Marguerite Trough, and it did not export larvae northward.</p> <p>This isolation has real implications. The MB krill population is largely self-sustaining in terms of larval supply. It doesn’t depend on transport from the north, but it also doesn’t contribute larvae to the northern Peninsula nurseries. The two ends of the wAP, despite being part of the same continental shelf system, are functionally separated when it comes to early life stage connectivity.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="the-connectivity-picture">The connectivity picture</h3> <p>Pulling across all years and nursery grounds, a consistent picture emerged:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Bransfield Strait and Marguerite Bay</strong> functioned as both spawning and nursery grounds, with strong self-retention. Most larvae that used these nurseries were spawned within them.</li> <li><strong>Off-shelf spawning</strong> could contribute larvae to nursery grounds, but only when wind conditions permitted.</li> <li><strong>Coastal larval transport</strong> generally moved north to south, with BS acting as a potential upstream source for the middle nursery grounds.</li> <li><strong>Marguerite Bay larvae remained isolated</strong> from the northern Antarctic Peninsula. No northward export was observed.</li> </ul> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/import-export-pathway-summary-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/import-export-pathway-summary-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/connectivity/import-export-pathway-summary-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/connectivity/import-export-pathway-summary.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Lagrangian drifter simulation design" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Primary trajectories of larvae (620 μm embryos) (A) into and (B) out of all nursery grounds </div> <hr/> <h3 id="what-strengthening-westerlies-could-mean">What strengthening westerlies could mean</h3> <p>The wind-driven variability we simulated could be a preview of the kind of shifts that climate change is projected to amplify.</p> <p>Westerly winds over the Southern Ocean are projected to strengthen and shift poleward through the end of the 21st century. Our results suggest this could have direct consequences for larval connectivity along the wAP. In the northern Antarctic Peninsula, seasonal winds modified larval transport pathways: when larvae weren’t advected north, they were transported toward the southern end of the Peninsula instead. Enhanced westerlies could reduce the frequency of southerly wind-driven transport from the Weddell Sea into the Bransfield Strait, instead favoring stronger along-slope currents that bypass Boyd Strait entirely.</p> <p>The connectivity pathways we observed, particularly the wind-sensitive ones supplying the Bransfield Strait, could be disrupted, with cascading implications for krill recruitment in the northern Peninsula.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="where-this-goes-next">Where this goes next</h3> <p>This circumpolar model gave us the proof of concept: our model can simulate connectivity between spawning and nursery grounds within the bounds of observed patterns. But the 5 km resolution and 25×25 km drifter spacing leave fine-scale dynamics unresolved. The next step is to take these questions into a high-resolution regional model, resolving the mesoscale circulation, complex coastline interactions, and bathymetric details that matter for larval retention and exchange at the scale where nursery grounds actually function.</p> <p>For more on the broader research program, see the <a href="/projects/krill-connectivity">project page</a>.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publications"/><category term="antarctica"/><category term="krill"/><category term="larvae"/><category term="connectivity"/><category term="ocean-modeling"/><category term="western-antarctic-peninsula"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A new paper in MEPS uses ocean modeling and particle tracking to show how bathymetry, embryo size, and wind variability shape larval krill connectivity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What goes here</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/what-goes-here/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What goes here"/><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/what-goes-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/what-goes-here/"><![CDATA[<p>Most of an academic website is a list of publications, maybe some talks, a bio. But a lot of what actually makes up research, like the in-between thinking, the half-formed ideas, the context that didn’t make it into a paper, the side projects and collaborations, doesn’t really have a home.</p> <p>This is that home, or at least an attempt at one. No particular schedule, no theme. Just the parts of the work that would otherwise stay in a notebook somewhere. It’s a learning experience in website building using jekyll/github/etc. I have no idea what I am doing, so any inconsistencies across any and all of this site are because this is a work in progress.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A short note on what this space is for.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Antarctic Ecosystem Value Index is published in Nature Communications</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/natcomms-aev-index/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Antarctic Ecosystem Value Index is published in Nature Communications"/><published>2026-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/natcomms-aev-index</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/natcomms-aev-index/"><![CDATA[<p>I am thrilled to share that a paper I helped write <strong>“An Antarctic ecosystem value index to quantify ecological value across trophic levels and over time”</strong> is now published in <em>Nature Communications</em>.</p> <blockquote> <p>DuVivier, A.K., Krumhardt, K., Landrum, L.L., Sylvester, Z. et al. (2026). An Antarctic ecosystem value index to quantify ecological value across trophic levels and over time. <em>Nature Communications.</em> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-69011-0">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-69011-0</a></p> </blockquote> <p>This paper is the scientific backbone of a <a href="/projects/hotspots-in-the-ice">larger project</a> we’ve been building for several years. Here’s what we found in our paper, why it matters, and what you can do with it.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="the-problem-we-set-out-to-solve">The Problem We Set Out to Solve</h3> <p>The Southern Ocean is changing faster than almost anywhere else on Earth. Sea ice is shifting. Productivity is reorganizing. Fisheries pressure is growing. And the international bodies charged with managing Antarctic marine resources — particularly <a href="https://www.ccamlr.org/">CCAMLR</a> — need science that can answer a deceptively simple question: <strong>where is the most ecologically valuable habitat, and will it still be valuable in the future?</strong></p> <p>Previous work had looked at individual species or single trophic levels. We wanted a holistic picture — something that captured ecosystem value from the bottom of the food web to the top, across space and through time.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="what-we-built-the-antarctic-ecosystem-value-index">What We Built: The Antarctic Ecosystem Value Index</h3> <p>The AEV Index integrates ecosystem information across trophic levels — from phytoplankton through krill and fish, up to penguins — to produce a single spatial score of ecological value for marine areas around the Antarctic continent.</p> <p>The key findings:</p> <p><strong>Polynyas are the hotspots.</strong> Coastal polynyas — the persistent patches of open water within the sea ice — have Index values <strong>31–72% higher</strong> than surrounding areas. These aren’t just physically interesting features; they are biologically critical ones, concentrating productivity and supporting ice-dependent species across the food web.</p> <p><strong>High-value areas are likely to persist.</strong> Using Earth System Model projections, we find that locations with high Index values today are generally likely to remain high-value through the end of the 21st century, despite substantial environmental change. This is not uniformly good news — it reflects the importance of protecting these places <em>now</em>, before conditions shift further.</p> <p><strong>Penguins are the canary.</strong> The Index reveals that penguin habitat suitability is already declining in some regions and is projected to deteriorate further. Because penguins integrate so many aspects of ecosystem health — prey availability, ice conditions, breeding habitat — their loss of importance in the Index is a meaningful signal about broader ecosystem change.</p> <p><strong>Protection gaps exist.</strong> While many high-value Index areas fall within existing or proposed MPAs, the analysis identifies clear opportunities for additional protection — particularly in <strong>East Antarctica</strong> and the <strong>Amundsen Sea</strong>, two regions that are ecologically important but currently without dedicated MPA proposals.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="why-this-approach-matters">Why This Approach Matters</h3> <p>Building an index that spans trophic levels required making deliberate choices about how to weight and combine fundamentally different types of data. We were intentional about developing this work iteratively, in dialogue with CCAMLR working groups over multiple years, so that the analytical choices reflected what would actually be useful for decision-making — not just what was methodologically convenient.</p> <p>The result is a science product that is simultaneously a research contribution and a decision support tool. The Index isn’t meant to replace expert judgment; it’s meant to give that judgment better spatial and temporal grounding.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="the-tools-built-on-this-science">The Tools Built on This Science</h3> <p>The paper is the foundation, but we also built two platforms to make this science accessible and actionable:</p> <p><strong><a href="https://only.one/map/antarctica-ecoindex#3.7/-85/169">The AEV Interactive Map</a></strong> — explore the Index across species layers and flip between present-day and 2090 projections. Accompanied by narrative stories about each focal region.</p> <p><strong><a href="https://saef-monash.shinyapps.io/antarctic_map/">The Index Comparison Tool</a></strong> — compare the AEV Index against all major circumpolar biodiversity analyses and bioregionalizations, and calculate quantitative overlap with any CCAMLR MPA planning domain or existing/proposed MPA.</p> <p>All underlying data are freely available: <a href="https://zenodo.org/records/16990591">https://zenodo.org/records/16990591</a></p> <hr/> <h3 id="whats-next">What’s Next</h3> <p>This paper is part of a cluster of work coming out of our NASA-funded project. A companion methods paper — on the challenges of identifying Antarctic coastal polynyas in satellite and model data — is also in press in <em>The Cryosphere</em> (Landrum et al., in press). That work underpins the physical polynya data layer used in the AEV Index, and it deserves its own post, which is coming soon.</p> <p>For a full overview of the project — including the interactive tools, team, and data — see the <a href="/projects/hotspots-in-the-ice">project page on this site</a>.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This work was funded by NASA Applied Sciences, Biodiversity and Ecological Forecasting (Grant 80NSSC21K1132). The paper is open access.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publications"/><category term="antarctica"/><category term="krill"/><category term="polynyas"/><category term="marine-conservation"/><category term="open-access"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping the ecological hotspots of Antarctica — present and future.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amundsen Sea Dynamics</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/amundsen-sea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amundsen Sea Dynamics"/><published>2026-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/amundsen-sea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/amundsen-sea/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="summary-of-amundsen-sea-dynamics">Summary of Amundsen Sea Dynamics</h2> <p>The Amundsen Sea features a strong seasonal sea-ice cycle with large coastal polynyas that open each summer and form episodically in winter; they are not permanently open year‑round. Polynyas are wind‑ and buoyancy‑driven, shaped by local bathymetry and grounded ice, and recent decades show regionally variable changes linked to winds and coastal freshwater fluxes.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="seasonal-ice-cycle">Seasonal ice cycle</h2> <p>The Amundsen Sea shows a pronounced seasonal cycle of ice advance and retreat that controls polynya occurrence and biological seasons. Open‑water polynyas recur every austral summer, while winter months host intense ice production during episodic open events.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Timing</strong> Most ice production associated with the Amundsen Sea Polynya occurs in austral autumn and spring, with large contributions in April–May and September–October, and the polynya opens in all observed summers [1].</li> <li><strong>Open‑water season length</strong> The central Amundsen Polynya averaged a longer open‑water season (~132 days) than the Pine Island Polynya (~122 days) in a 1997–2010 satellite record, with large interannual variability in both polynyas [2].</li> <li><strong>Ice formation rates</strong> Observations and a one‑dimensional budget estimate intense heat loss and ice formation in the polynya mixed layer (order centimeters per day during autumn) driven by air–sea heat fluxes and lateral advection [3].</li> <li><strong>Regional variability</strong> Multi‑decadal analyses show spatially varying trends (decreases and increases) across the Amundsen Sea, indicating different local forcings for ice advance/retreat in different sectors [4].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="polynya-formation-mechanisms">Polynya formation mechanisms</h2> <p>Polynyas in the Amundsen Sea form from a combination of atmospheric forcing, oceanic processes, and coastal geometry. Both wind‑driven coastal opening and ocean‑driven upwelling/buoyancy signals contribute, with local bathymetry and icebergs focusing the response.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Wind opening</strong> Strong, persistent southeasterly or easterly winds can drive coastal polynyas by advecting sea ice away from the coast and exposing open water, sometimes producing large winter polynya events [1].</li> <li><strong>Atmospheric heat loss</strong> Surface heat loss to the atmosphere over open water accelerates mixed‑layer cooling and sea‑ice formation in autumn/winter, reinforcing polynya production [3] [5].</li> <li><strong>Oceanic upwelling and warm water</strong> Upwelling of warm deep/shelf waters near ice fronts can maintain localized open areas and explain persistent polynya locations at some ice‑shelf fronts [6].</li> <li><strong>Buoyancy and meltwater influences</strong> Freshwater from melting ice shelves (the “meltwater pump”) and buoyancy forcing modulate stratification and can help sustain or seed polynyas and associated biological productivity [7] [5].</li> <li><strong>Bathymetry and grounded icebergs</strong> Local bathymetric highs and chains of grounded icebergs act as fixed geometrical anchors for recurring polynya formation by influencing ice‑outflow pathways and creating secondary openings [1].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="polynya-temporal-persistence">Polynya temporal persistence</h2> <p>Polynyas in the Amundsen Sea are largely seasonal and episodic rather than permanently open. Their persistence depends on season, wind events, and broader sea‑ice conditions.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Seasonal recurrence</strong> The main coastal polynya opens every summer but typically closes or is covered by new or advected ice outside the open‑water season [1].</li> <li><strong>Not year‑round</strong> While some ice‑shelf front locations show persistent warm‑water‑related openings in imagery, the large embayment‑scale Amundsen Sea Polynya does not remain continuously open year‑round in the satellite era [6] [1].</li> <li><strong>Episodic winter events</strong> During winter, intense polynya activity and most ice production occur in concentrated months (notably April–May and September–October), though strong wind events can trigger additional winter openings [1].</li> <li><strong>Local trapping and closure</strong> Ice produced within the polynya can become trapped nearby or advected back into it, which can lead to temporary closure and modulate the apparent persistence of open water [1].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="key-driving-factors-and-recent-trends">Key driving factors and recent trends</h2> <p>Winds, ocean heat and freshwater, and coastal geometry jointly control polynya behavior; recent observations and models indicate regional trends and feedbacks that affect ice‑shelf melt and thermocline variability. Changes in wind patterns and sea‑ice freshwater fluxes have been linked to decadal shifts in shelf stratification and ice‑shelf melt regimes.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Winds</strong> Strong coastal winds are primary triggers for coastal polynyas and their winter intensity; changes in wind timing and direction have altered sea‑ice advance/retreat and polynya timing in parts of the Amundsen Sea [1] [4].</li> <li><strong>Ocean heat and upwelling</strong> Delivery of warm deep shelf waters to ice fronts sustains basal melting and can create localized persistent openings; conversely, polynya‑driven surface cooling and freshwater fluxes can modulate the thermocline and warm water volume near ice shelves [6] [8] [9].</li> <li><strong>Bathymetry and grounded ice</strong> Fixed bathymetric highs and grounded iceberg chains localize polynya formation and influence ice outflow pathways and secondary polynya creation [1].</li> <li><strong>Freshwater feedbacks</strong> Variability in sea‑ice formation and meltwater influences cross‑shelf density gradients and can drive interannual to decadal changes in shelf circulation and ice‑shelf melt rates via feedbacks with polynya buoyancy forcing [8] [9].</li> <li><strong>Biophysical interactions and recent observations</strong> High phytoplankton biomass in polynyas enhances surface warming in spring–summer, alters seasonal heat budgets, and can feed back to seasonal ice‑volume changes; satellite and in situ records show large interannual variability but no simple monotonic trend in polynya productivity over the limited observational record [10] [2] [5].</li> <li><strong>Long‑term variability</strong> Ice‑core proxies and satellite records reveal interannual to decadal variability in polynya size and timing, tied to local wind forcing and coastal icescape changes, indicating that polynya behavior has shifted regionally over the satellite era [11] [4] [2].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol> <li>Macdonald, G. J., Ackley, S. F., and Mestas-Nuñez, A. M. (2021). Evolution of the Amundsen Sea Polynya, Antarctica, 2016–2021. <em>The Cryosphere Discussions</em>, 1–33. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/TC-2021-250">doi:10.5194/TC-2021-250</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J., Ackley, S. F., Mestas-Nuñez, A. M., and Blanco-Cabanillas, A. (2023). Evolution of the dynamics, area, and ice production of the Amundsen Sea Polynya, Antarctica, 2016–2021. <em>The Cryosphere</em>, 17(2), 457–476. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-17-457-2023">doi:10.5194/tc-17-457-2023</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J. (2022). Reply on RC1. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac1">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac1</a></li> <li>St-Laurent, P., Klinck, J. M., and Dinniman, M. S. (2015). Impact of local winter cooling on the melt of Pine Island Glacier, Antarctica. <em>Journal of Geophysical Research</em>, 120(10), 6718–6732. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/2015JC010709">doi:10.1002/2015JC010709</a></li> <li>Comment on tc-2022-51. (2022). <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-rc1">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-rc1</a></li> <li>Jones, R. Weather and climate in the Amundsen Sea Embayment, West Antarctica: observations, reanalyses and high resolution modelling. <a href="https://ueaeprints.uea.ac.uk/id/eprint/66998/">Available online</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J. (2022). Reply on RC3. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac2">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac2</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J. (2022). Reply on RC1. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac4">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac4</a></li> <li>Criscitiello, A. S. et al. (2013). Ice sheet record of recent sea-ice behavior and polynya variability in the Amundsen Sea, West Antarctica. <em>Journal of Geophysical Research</em>, 118(1), 118–130. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2012JC008077">doi:10.1029/2012JC008077</a></li> <li>Zheng, Y., Webber, B. G. M., Heywood, K. J., Stevens, D. P., Stammerjohn, S., and Hall, R. (2024). Upper-ocean processes and sea ice production in the southeastern Amundsen Sea Polynya in austral autumn. <em>Journal of Physical Oceanography</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1175/jpo-d-24-0006.1">doi:10.1175/jpo-d-24-0006.1</a></li> <li>Björk, M. y M., Fransson, A., Torstensson, A., and Chierici, M. (2014). Ocean acidification state in western Antarctic surface waters: controls and interannual variability. <em>Biogeosciences</em>, 11(1), 57–73. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/BG-11-57-2014">doi:10.5194/BG-11-57-2014</a></li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review"/><category term="research-notebook"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A literature review of Amundsen Sea polynya dynamics, seasonal ice cycles, and recent trends.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Krill Expert Group Advances Antarctic Krill Management Framework at CCAMLR | SCAR</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/krill-expert-group-advances-antarctic-krill-management-framework-at-ccamlr-scar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Krill Expert Group Advances Antarctic Krill Management Framework at CCAMLR | SCAR"/><published>2025-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/krill-expert-group-advances-antarctic-krill-management-framework-at-ccamlr--scar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/krill-expert-group-advances-antarctic-krill-management-framework-at-ccamlr-scar/"><![CDATA[<p>Home &gt; News &gt; Krill Expert Group Advances Antarctic Krill Management Framework at CCAMLRShare this pagePost navigationInterested in contributing to SCAR?Sign up to our free monthly newsletter here:SCAR.orgOur ServicesResourcesGet In Touch TEL: +44 1223 336550 [email protected] Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research, Scott Polar Research Institute, University of Cambridge, Lensfield Road, Cambridge, CB2 1ER, United Kingdom |  © Copyright 2026 SCAR | Website by Union 10 Design</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="policy"/><category term="krill"/><category term="CCAMLR"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Just a moment…</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/just-a-moment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Just a moment…"/><published>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/just-a-moment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/just-a-moment/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="policy"/><category term="krill"/><category term="media"/><category term="science-communication"/><category term="interactive"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Untangling how Antarctic krill survive the winter — and what climate change means for their future</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/overwintering-krill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Untangling how Antarctic krill survive the winter — and what climate change means for their future"/><published>2025-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/overwintering-krill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/overwintering-krill/"><![CDATA[<p>Antarctic krill are small. About the size of your pinky finger. But they hold up an entire ocean.</p> <p>Every penguin, seal, whale, and seabird in the Southern Ocean depends, directly or indirectly, on <em>Euphausia superba</em>. And every krill alive today survived something remarkably precarious: their first winter.</p> <p>Our paper, published in <em>ICES Journal of Marine Science</em> in April 2025, takes a close look at that survival challenge — and at what happens to it as the ocean warms and sea ice disappears.</p> <blockquote> <p>Sylvester, Z., et al. (2025). Untangling larval Antarctic krill overwinter survival under climate change using a qualitative network model. <em>ICES Journal of Marine Science</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/icesjms/fsaf049">https://doi.org/10.1093/icesjms/fsaf049</a></p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h3 id="the-short-version">The short version</h3> <p>Winters with extensive sea ice have long been linked to strong krill recruitment the following spring. But <em>why</em>? Sea ice does a lot of things at once — it provides food (ice algae), shelter from predators (in ice terraces and under-ice habitat), and physical structure that shapes the water column. Untangling which of these mechanisms matters most, and how their loss will affect larval survival differently in different habitats, is exactly what this paper attempts.</p> <p>We used a <strong>qualitative network model (QNM)</strong> — a framework that lets you integrate both well-established and hypothesized ecological interactions and test what the system predicts under different scenarios, even when you don’t have the quantitative data to parameterize a full simulation model.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center mt-4"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Untangling krill overwinter survival — infographic" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The full story in one image. Art by [Sven Bellanger](www.SvenBellanger.be). See below for a guided walk-through of each piece. </div> <p>The headline findings:</p> <ul> <li><strong>The northern Antarctic Peninsula continental shelf is most at risk.</strong> Reduced autumn primary productivity and warming temperatures under future climate scenarios drive substantial declines in larval survival in this habitat.</li> <li><strong>Open-ocean habitats may see improved survival under cooler scenarios</strong> — where sea-ice-associated processes like food availability and under-ice refuge remain intact.</li> <li><strong>Hypothesized mechanisms matter.</strong> Including sea-ice terraces as potential predation refuges in the model <em>strengthened</em> the projected declines — suggesting that the loss of ice structure may matter as much as the loss of ice algae.</li> <li><strong>Glacial melt is an unresolved uncertainty.</strong> Its influence on food web dynamics emerged as a critical knowledge gap that future field and lab work should target.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h3 id="want-to-go-deeper">Want to go deeper?</h3> <p>The rest of this post walks through the paper’s logic in more detail — the biology, the model structure, and what the results mean for each habitat. I’ve broken it into sections so you can read as much or as little as you want.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="why-winter-is-the-bottleneck">Why winter is the bottleneck</h2> <p>Circumpolar krill populations grow each year through the recruitment of the previous year’s juvenile class. Four things shape how many juveniles make it into the adult population: spawning success and larval development in spring and summer, how well-prepared krill are heading into winter, and — the focus of this paper — how many larvae actually survive it.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/seasonal-cycles-overwintering-ZTS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/seasonal-cycles-overwintering-ZTS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/seasonal-cycles-overwintering-ZTS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/seasonal-cycles-overwintering-ZTS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Krill seasonal population dynamics" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Krill population dynamics: circumpolar krill populations increase each year through the recruitment of the previous year's juvenile class. </div> <p>Winter in the Southern Ocean is brutal for anything small and hungry. With little to no sunlight, primary productivity essentially shuts down — and with it, the food web that krill depend on.</p> <p>Adult krill have a strategy for this: they spend autumn eating as much as they can, building up lipid reserves from energy-rich prey like diatoms. Once winter hits, they stop feeding altogether and draw down those stores. They even <em>shrink</em> — physically reducing their body size to conserve energy until the light returns. It’s a remarkable adaptation, but it only works because adults have the body mass to accumulate meaningful reserves in the first place.</p> <p>Larvae don’t have that option. Too small to build lipid stores, they must keep feeding continuously throughout the winter — even when food is almost nowhere to be found. What little food is available to them comes largely from algae that has been trapped in sea ice and is slowly released as the ice melts, or from microzooplankton persisting in the water column.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Fall-Winter-recruitement-ZTS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Fall-Winter-recruitement-ZTS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Fall-Winter-recruitement-ZTS-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Fall-Winter-recruitement-ZTS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Krill overwintering strategies by age class" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Krill have different overwintering strategies depending on their age: adults have lipid stores to sustain them through winter; larvae don't — and must keep feeding to survive. </div> <p>This is what makes winter the critical bottleneck for recruitment. Sea ice isn’t just frozen water — for larval krill, it’s a food source, a refuge from predators, and in some cases a physical habitat. As sea ice declines and becomes less predictable under climate change, understanding exactly <em>which</em> of these roles matters most — and <em>where</em> — becomes urgently important.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-mechanisms-control-overwinter-survival">What mechanisms control overwinter survival?</h2> <p>Food and shelter — that’s the short answer. Sea ice facilitates larval overwinter survival and subsequent recruitment by providing both.</p> <p>During the winter months, a larval krill’s ability to survive comes down to two things: access to sea ice algae as a food source, and the ability to avoid predation. The prevailing paradigm in krill biology centers on exactly this — that sea ice habitat is what makes larval survival possible, and that years with extensive, stable sea ice produce strong recruitment classes the following spring.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/food-shelter-ZTS-Ulrich-Frieir-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/food-shelter-ZTS-Ulrich-Frieir-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/food-shelter-ZTS-Ulrich-Frieir-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/food-shelter-ZTS-Ulrich-Frieir.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Krill swarming on the underside of sea ice" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Krill swarming on the underside of sea ice — exactly the habitat that the prevailing paradigm puts at the center of larval overwinter survival. Photo: Ulrich Freier; art by Zephyr Sylvester. </div> <p>That image captures something remarkable: krill aggregating on the underside of the ice, grazing on algae growing in and just below the ice surface. The ice isn’t just a backdrop, it’s actively being used, as food source and as physical structure that offers some refuge from the open water below where predators hunt.</p> <p>But this paradigm, compelling as it is, raises a harder question: <em>which</em> of these mechanisms matters most? Is it the food, the shelter, or the physical habitat structure itself? And does the answer differ depending on where in the Southern Ocean the larvae are?</p> <p>That’s what our model was designed to untangle.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-is-a-qualitative-network-model--and-why-use-one">What is a qualitative network model — and why use one?</h2> <p>It is unknown what adaptations larval krill have to survive the overwintering period and what impacts decreases in sea ice may have on krill recruitment. Current theories on overwintering mechanisms include:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Autumn food availability</strong> — krill must build condition before winter arrives</li> <li><strong>Sea ice algae as a major energy source</strong> — ice-associated algae as a critical winter food subsidy for larvae</li> <li><strong>Alternate food sources</strong> — microzooplankton and other pelagic prey when ice algae is unavailable</li> <li><strong>Habitat flexibility</strong> — larval distribution shifting between under-ice and pelagic depending on the harshness of winter conditions</li> </ul> <p>Each of these mechanisms carries different implications for how krill recruitment responds to environmental change, and in particular the role of sea ice.</p> <p>While some empirical work has been done and some models have been tested, more clarity is needed in understanding how uncertain mechanisms may impact model predictions.</p> <p>This brings me to my research question: <strong>What is the impact of uncertainty in the mechanisms controlling overwintering survival on future projections of recruitment success?</strong></p> <hr/> <h3 id="how-can-the-impact-of-uncertainty-in-the-mechanisms-controlling-overwintering-survival-be-quantified">How can the impact of uncertainty in the mechanisms controlling overwintering survival be quantified?</h3> <p>So how do we attempt to answer a question like this? We wanted to test three things: knowns vs. unknowns, the region most important to krill, and climate change scenarios.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/figure_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/figure_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/figure_2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/figure_2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Antarctic krill habitat zones" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Antarctic krill habitat zones within the southwest Atlantic sector of the Southern Ocean used within the modelling simulation. </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Table1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Table1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Table1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Table1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Climate change scenarios" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The climate change scenarios simulated in this study by applying combinations of press perturbations to climate driver nodes. </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center"> <blockquote class="blockquote text-center"> <p class="mb-0">Relationships: Evidenced vs Hypothesized</p> </blockquote> </div> </div> <p>In order to test these three things in a non-computationally expensive way while still capturing the complexity of the ecosystem, we developed a qualitative network model (QNM) that simplifies ecological relationships into their essential structure.</p> <h3 id="our-qualitative-network-analysis-framework">Our Qualitative Network Analysis Framework</h3> <p>The approach follows five steps:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Tabulate all interactions</strong> — compile every relevant ecological relationship from the literature</li> <li><strong>Identify uncertain interactions</strong> — classify each by the level of certainty based on literature, expert knowledge, and observational data</li> <li><strong>Evaluate models</strong> — test the network structure with and without uncertain mechanisms</li> <li><strong>Aggregate results</strong> — combine outputs across model variants</li> <li><strong>Analyze</strong> — interpret what the range of model structures tells us about system behavior</li> </ol> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Figure-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Figure-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Figure-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/Figure-1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="QNM interaction network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Our QNM tabulates interactions critical for understanding the impacts on larval survival and growth over the winter. </div> <p>Once all possible interactions have been determined via an extensive literature review, interactions are classified based on the level of uncertainty as determined by the literature, expert knowledge, and observational data. This creates varying model structures that explicitly account for the level of certainty in the relationship between response variables.</p> <p>The neat thing about a QNM is that it’s computationally inexpensive which means we could include more complex features like sea ice convergence and terraces in the model without it becoming prohibitively costly to run.</p> <p>We then ran simulations across each habitat of interest, for all climate change scenarios, with and without the uncertain mechanisms and set about answering our questions.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-will-happen-to-larval-overwintering-habitat-in-the-future">What will happen to larval overwintering habitat in the future?</h2> <p>Habitat suitability for larval krill will decrease under all scenarios, particularly in the Northern Antarctic Peninsula. Out of all the possible relationships in the model, the one with the most influence on this result was the projected decrease in seasonal primary productivity: less food available in autumn means larvae arrive at winter already behind.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="how-can-we-improve-our-understanding-of-larval-overwintering">How can we improve our understanding of larval overwintering?</h2> <p>This highlights how a single hypothesized mechanism can invert baseline projections — and underscores the importance of refining our understanding of the processes linking sea ice features, predator avoidance, and larval krill performance.</p> <p>The two areas of greatest uncertainty that future work should target are:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Food availability and composition</strong> — what larvae are actually eating in winter, and how that changes as ice declines</li> <li><strong>Predation risk and sea ice terraces</strong> — whether ice structure provides meaningful refuge, and what is lost when that structure disappears</li> </ul> <p>This is especially pertinent in the Northern Antarctic Peninsula, where habitat suitability is projected to decline due to reduced food availability — making it the region where resolving these uncertainties matters most.</p> <p>Which brings us back to where we started:</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center mt-4"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/projects/overwintering/untangling-infographic.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Untangling krill overwinter survival — infographic" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The full picture: food, shelter, habitat, and the mechanisms we still need to untangle. Art by [Sven Bellanger](www.SvenBellanger.be). </div> <p>The infographic tells the story we couldn’t tell with equations alone. The QNM gave us a framework for holding competing hypotheses at once; the infographic makes visible why that complexity matters. Both are trying to do the same thing: make the invisible winter world of a larval krill a little more legible. —</p> <p><em>This paper was produced as part of my dissertation research.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publications"/><category term="antarctica"/><category term="krill"/><category term="sea-ice"/><category term="recruitment"/><category term="climate-change"/><category term="southern-ocean"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A qualitative network model reveals habitat-specific winners and losers as sea ice declines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tiny Antarctic Krill Benefit the Planet in Big Ways, but Face a Barrage of Threats</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/tiny-antarctic-krill-benefit-the-planet-in-big-ways-but-face-a-barrage-of-threats/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tiny Antarctic Krill Benefit the Planet in Big Ways, but Face a Barrage of Threats"/><published>2025-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/tiny-antarctic-krill-benefit-the-planet-in-big-ways-but-face-a-barrage-of-threats</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/tiny-antarctic-krill-benefit-the-planet-in-big-ways-but-face-a-barrage-of-threats/"><![CDATA[<p>SectionsMore from Smithsonian magazineOur PartnersSubscribe to Smithsonian magazine and get a FREE tote.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Gabe Castro-Root
    
    
      
    
    A single Antarctic krill is about the size of your pinky finger. But with an estimated population of more than 700 trillion in the Southern Ocean, the tiny crustacean’s collective impact across the entire planet is enormous.Their swarms are so massive they can be seen from space. They’re food by the millions for seals and penguins and whales. And they sequester huge amounts of carbon—more than $15 billion worth per year, according to the World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF).Increasingly, though, Antarctic krill face threats from warming seas and a growing fishery. Scientists say that without international action to bolster marine protected areas and combat climate change, krill populations—and the resulting carbon sequestration—could drop off sharply in the coming decades.Antarctic krill act as one of the world’s largest “biological pumps,” a term scientists use to describe the process by which marine organisms send carbon to the depths of the ocean, where it can be stored for hundreds of years. A study published last September in Nature Communications found that Antarctic krill sequester similar amounts of carbon to coastal marshes, mangroves and seagrass, habitats scientists consider some of the planet’s most prolific carbon sinks.Krill feed on phytoplankton, which, like land-based plants, consume carbon dioxide and release oxygen as they photosynthesize. When krill waste sinks to the bottom of the ocean, all that carbon goes with it, essentially locking it away and freeing up space at the surface for more carbon to be absorbed from the air.“Krill are, by fact of life, living and molting and pooping and dying, and all that is very important to bring carbon from the surface ocean to the deep sea,” says Matthew Savoca, an ecologist at Stanford University. “When krill are doing that at the population level, they end up being an important ally in the climate change fight.”But Antarctic krill also face a host of challenges, including from warming oceans and an emboldened fishing industry, that researchers say require urgent attention. A study led by researchers at the British Antarctic Survey, published in Marine Pollution Bulletin this past December, found that an increase in plastic pollution in the Southern Ocean could inhibit krill’s ability to sequester carbon by 27 percent.While the sheer number of krill in the Southern Ocean means the species is unlikely to face an acute threat to its survival in the near term, Savoca is quick to point out that numbers are no guarantee of success.“You only have to look as far as our own country for the story of passenger pigeons to show you how quickly something can go from being incredibly abundant to extinct,” he says.The Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources, which regulates fishing activity in the Southern Ocean, failed at a meeting last October to renew a key measure aimed at preventing excessive krill harvests in any one area. The commission, which makes decisions by consensus among its 26 member states and the European Union, has been at a yearslong standstill over that measure and several proposed marine protected areas amid opposition from China and Russia.The result, says Zephyr Sylvester, an environmental researcher at the University of Colorado Boulder, is that fishing vessels are free to act on their companies’ directives until a new regulation is adopted. The lack of enforcement could allow the fishery to concentrate operations in a smaller area where it would have a larger environmental impact, she says.Krill are used in products ranging from nutritional supplements to livestock feed, and the WWF estimates the Antarctic krill fishery to be worth about $250 million annually.“We’ll learn a lot about the integrity of the fishery” now that the conservation measure has lapsed, Sylvester says, adding that external pressure, like the diplomatic and public awareness campaign in support of the Ross Sea Region Marine Protected Area a decade ago, remains among the most effective methods to turn scientists’ recommendations into policy. Still, she says, “it shouldn’t be the burden of consumers to enforce sustainable fishing practices.”At the same time, declining sea ice is exacerbating challenges for Antarctic krill from the earliest stages of life. Krill larvae don’t have the lipid reserves of adult krill to get through the dark Antarctic winter, says Hauke Flores, a marine biologist at the Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research in Bremerhaven, Germany. Instead, larvae stick to the sea ice, feeding on ice algae until the sun—and the phytoplankton—returns in spring.“Sea ice is critically important for Antarctic krill,” Flores says. “Without these algae that grow inside the sea ice, they will simply not survive.”The Antarctic Peninsula, which juts northward and where huge numbers of krill are concentrated, is warming five times faster than the global average, according to research backed by the National Science Foundation. As a result, scientists say, krill may be concentrating farther south in search of more stable sea ice. A 2023 study in Nature Reviews Earth &amp; Environment found that changes in the distribution of krill around Antarctica, driven by warming waters, threatened to increase interactions between fishing vessels and the animals that feed on krill, such as whales and penguins.The study’s lead author, So Kawaguchi, a krill ecologist at the Australian Antarctic Division, says scientists are still trying to understand exactly how climate change will affect Antarctic krill. From his lab in Tasmania, where he has a research aquarium filled with 20,000 krill, Kawaguchi has shown that, if carbon emissions remain unchecked, krill hatch rates in parts of the Southern Ocean could decrease by 70 percent within the next century.But he cautions that the effort to decode Antarctica’s shifting marine ecosystems is still in its early stages.“There are lots of other things we need to consider,” he says. “It’s just the start.”
        Gabe Castro-Root
        
        | Read More
      Email Powered by Salesforce Marketing Cloud (Privacy Notice / Terms &amp; Conditions)Follow UsExploreSubscriptionNewslettersAboutOur Partners
    © 2026 Smithsonian Magazine
  
      Privacy Statement [5/20/25]

  

  
  
      Cookie Policy [5/20/25]

  

  
  
      Terms of Use

  

  
  
      Advertising Notice

  

  
  
      Your Privacy Rights

  
Cookie Settings
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="krill"/><category term="media"/><category term="science-communication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The bountiful creatures sequester carbon and are a vital food source for marine predators, but their future is uncertain]]></summary></entry></feed>