<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-17T05:54:47+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">What goes here</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/what-goes-here/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What goes here"/><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/what-goes-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/what-goes-here/"><![CDATA[<p>Most of an academic website is a list of publications, maybe some talks, a bio. But a lot of what actually makes up research — the in-between thinking, the half-formed ideas, the context that didn’t make it into a paper — doesn’t really have a home.</p> <p>This is that home, or at least an attempt at one. No particular schedule, no theme. Just the parts of the work that would otherwise stay in a notebook somewhere. It’s a learning experience in website building using jekyll/github/etc. I have no idea what I am doing, so any inconsistencies across any and all of this site are because this is a work in progress.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A short note on what this space is for.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amundsen Sea Dynamics</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/amundsen-sea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amundsen Sea Dynamics"/><published>2026-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/amundsen-sea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2026/amundsen-sea/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="summary-of-amundsen-sea-dynamics">Summary of Amundsen Sea Dynamics</h2> <p>The Amundsen Sea features a strong seasonal sea-ice cycle with large coastal polynyas that open each summer and form episodically in winter; they are not permanently open year‑round. Polynyas are wind‑ and buoyancy‑driven, shaped by local bathymetry and grounded ice, and recent decades show regionally variable changes linked to winds and coastal freshwater fluxes.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="seasonal-ice-cycle">Seasonal ice cycle</h2> <p>The Amundsen Sea shows a pronounced seasonal cycle of ice advance and retreat that controls polynya occurrence and biological seasons. Open‑water polynyas recur every austral summer, while winter months host intense ice production during episodic open events.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Timing</strong> Most ice production associated with the Amundsen Sea Polynya occurs in austral autumn and spring, with large contributions in April–May and September–October, and the polynya opens in all observed summers [1].</li> <li><strong>Open‑water season length</strong> The central Amundsen Polynya averaged a longer open‑water season (~132 days) than the Pine Island Polynya (~122 days) in a 1997–2010 satellite record, with large interannual variability in both polynyas [2].</li> <li><strong>Ice formation rates</strong> Observations and a one‑dimensional budget estimate intense heat loss and ice formation in the polynya mixed layer (order centimeters per day during autumn) driven by air–sea heat fluxes and lateral advection [3].</li> <li><strong>Regional variability</strong> Multi‑decadal analyses show spatially varying trends (decreases and increases) across the Amundsen Sea, indicating different local forcings for ice advance/retreat in different sectors [4].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="polynya-formation-mechanisms">Polynya formation mechanisms</h2> <p>Polynyas in the Amundsen Sea form from a combination of atmospheric forcing, oceanic processes, and coastal geometry. Both wind‑driven coastal opening and ocean‑driven upwelling/buoyancy signals contribute, with local bathymetry and icebergs focusing the response.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Wind opening</strong> Strong, persistent southeasterly or easterly winds can drive coastal polynyas by advecting sea ice away from the coast and exposing open water, sometimes producing large winter polynya events [1].</li> <li><strong>Atmospheric heat loss</strong> Surface heat loss to the atmosphere over open water accelerates mixed‑layer cooling and sea‑ice formation in autumn/winter, reinforcing polynya production [3] [5].</li> <li><strong>Oceanic upwelling and warm water</strong> Upwelling of warm deep/shelf waters near ice fronts can maintain localized open areas and explain persistent polynya locations at some ice‑shelf fronts [6].</li> <li><strong>Buoyancy and meltwater influences</strong> Freshwater from melting ice shelves (the “meltwater pump”) and buoyancy forcing modulate stratification and can help sustain or seed polynyas and associated biological productivity [7] [5].</li> <li><strong>Bathymetry and grounded icebergs</strong> Local bathymetric highs and chains of grounded icebergs act as fixed geometrical anchors for recurring polynya formation by influencing ice‑outflow pathways and creating secondary openings [1].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="polynya-temporal-persistence">Polynya temporal persistence</h2> <p>Polynyas in the Amundsen Sea are largely seasonal and episodic rather than permanently open. Their persistence depends on season, wind events, and broader sea‑ice conditions.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Seasonal recurrence</strong> The main coastal polynya opens every summer but typically closes or is covered by new or advected ice outside the open‑water season [1].</li> <li><strong>Not year‑round</strong> While some ice‑shelf front locations show persistent warm‑water‑related openings in imagery, the large embayment‑scale Amundsen Sea Polynya does not remain continuously open year‑round in the satellite era [6] [1].</li> <li><strong>Episodic winter events</strong> During winter, intense polynya activity and most ice production occur in concentrated months (notably April–May and September–October), though strong wind events can trigger additional winter openings [1].</li> <li><strong>Local trapping and closure</strong> Ice produced within the polynya can become trapped nearby or advected back into it, which can lead to temporary closure and modulate the apparent persistence of open water [1].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="key-driving-factors-and-recent-trends">Key driving factors and recent trends</h2> <p>Winds, ocean heat and freshwater, and coastal geometry jointly control polynya behavior; recent observations and models indicate regional trends and feedbacks that affect ice‑shelf melt and thermocline variability. Changes in wind patterns and sea‑ice freshwater fluxes have been linked to decadal shifts in shelf stratification and ice‑shelf melt regimes.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Winds</strong> Strong coastal winds are primary triggers for coastal polynyas and their winter intensity; changes in wind timing and direction have altered sea‑ice advance/retreat and polynya timing in parts of the Amundsen Sea [1] [4].</li> <li><strong>Ocean heat and upwelling</strong> Delivery of warm deep shelf waters to ice fronts sustains basal melting and can create localized persistent openings; conversely, polynya‑driven surface cooling and freshwater fluxes can modulate the thermocline and warm water volume near ice shelves [6] [8] [9].</li> <li><strong>Bathymetry and grounded ice</strong> Fixed bathymetric highs and grounded iceberg chains localize polynya formation and influence ice outflow pathways and secondary polynya creation [1].</li> <li><strong>Freshwater feedbacks</strong> Variability in sea‑ice formation and meltwater influences cross‑shelf density gradients and can drive interannual to decadal changes in shelf circulation and ice‑shelf melt rates via feedbacks with polynya buoyancy forcing [8] [9].</li> <li><strong>Biophysical interactions and recent observations</strong> High phytoplankton biomass in polynyas enhances surface warming in spring–summer, alters seasonal heat budgets, and can feed back to seasonal ice‑volume changes; satellite and in situ records show large interannual variability but no simple monotonic trend in polynya productivity over the limited observational record [10] [2] [5].</li> <li><strong>Long‑term variability</strong> Ice‑core proxies and satellite records reveal interannual to decadal variability in polynya size and timing, tied to local wind forcing and coastal icescape changes, indicating that polynya behavior has shifted regionally over the satellite era [11] [4] [2].</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol> <li>Macdonald, G. J., Ackley, S. F., and Mestas-Nuñez, A. M. (2021). Evolution of the Amundsen Sea Polynya, Antarctica, 2016–2021. <em>The Cryosphere Discussions</em>, 1–33. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/TC-2021-250">doi:10.5194/TC-2021-250</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J., Ackley, S. F., Mestas-Nuñez, A. M., and Blanco-Cabanillas, A. (2023). Evolution of the dynamics, area, and ice production of the Amundsen Sea Polynya, Antarctica, 2016–2021. <em>The Cryosphere</em>, 17(2), 457–476. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-17-457-2023">doi:10.5194/tc-17-457-2023</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J. (2022). Reply on RC1. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac1">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac1</a></li> <li>St-Laurent, P., Klinck, J. M., and Dinniman, M. S. (2015). Impact of local winter cooling on the melt of Pine Island Glacier, Antarctica. <em>Journal of Geophysical Research</em>, 120(10), 6718–6732. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/2015JC010709">doi:10.1002/2015JC010709</a></li> <li>Comment on tc-2022-51. (2022). <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-rc1">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-rc1</a></li> <li>Jones, R. Weather and climate in the Amundsen Sea Embayment, West Antarctica: observations, reanalyses and high resolution modelling. <a href="https://ueaeprints.uea.ac.uk/id/eprint/66998/">Available online</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J. (2022). Reply on RC3. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac2">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac2</a></li> <li>Macdonald, G. J. (2022). Reply on RC1. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac4">doi:10.5194/tc-2022-51-ac4</a></li> <li>Criscitiello, A. S. et al. (2013). Ice sheet record of recent sea-ice behavior and polynya variability in the Amundsen Sea, West Antarctica. <em>Journal of Geophysical Research</em>, 118(1), 118–130. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2012JC008077">doi:10.1029/2012JC008077</a></li> <li>Zheng, Y., Webber, B. G. M., Heywood, K. J., Stevens, D. P., Stammerjohn, S., and Hall, R. (2024). Upper-ocean processes and sea ice production in the southeastern Amundsen Sea Polynya in austral autumn. <em>Journal of Physical Oceanography</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1175/jpo-d-24-0006.1">doi:10.1175/jpo-d-24-0006.1</a></li> <li>Björk, M. y M., Fransson, A., Torstensson, A., and Chierici, M. (2014). Ocean acidification state in western Antarctic surface waters: controls and interannual variability. <em>Biogeosciences</em>, 11(1), 57–73. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/BG-11-57-2014">doi:10.5194/BG-11-57-2014</a></li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review"/><category term="research-notebook"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A literature review of Amundsen Sea polynya dynamics, seasonal ice cycles, and recent trends.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Krill Expert Group Advances Antarctic Krill Management Framework at CCAMLR | SCAR</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/krill-expert-group-advances-antarctic-krill-management-framework-at-ccamlr-scar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Krill Expert Group Advances Antarctic Krill Management Framework at CCAMLR | SCAR"/><published>2025-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/krill-expert-group-advances-antarctic-krill-management-framework-at-ccamlr--scar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/krill-expert-group-advances-antarctic-krill-management-framework-at-ccamlr-scar/"><![CDATA[<p>Home &gt; News &gt; Krill Expert Group Advances Antarctic Krill Management Framework at CCAMLRShare this pagePost navigationInterested in contributing to SCAR?Sign up to our free monthly newsletter here:SCAR.orgOur ServicesResourcesGet In Touch TEL: +44 1223 336550 [email protected] Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research, Scott Polar Research Institute, University of Cambridge, Lensfield Road, Cambridge, CB2 1ER, United Kingdom |  © Copyright 2026 SCAR | Website by Union 10 Design</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="policy"/><category term="krill"/><category term="CCAMLR"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Just a moment…</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/just-a-moment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Just a moment…"/><published>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/just-a-moment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/just-a-moment/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="policy"/><category term="krill"/><category term="media"/><category term="science-communication"/><category term="interactive"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Tiny Antarctic Krill Benefit the Planet in Big Ways, but Face a Barrage of Threats</title><link href="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/tiny-antarctic-krill-benefit-the-planet-in-big-ways-but-face-a-barrage-of-threats/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tiny Antarctic Krill Benefit the Planet in Big Ways, but Face a Barrage of Threats"/><published>2025-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/tiny-antarctic-krill-benefit-the-planet-in-big-ways-but-face-a-barrage-of-threats</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zephyr-sylvester.github.io/blog/2025/tiny-antarctic-krill-benefit-the-planet-in-big-ways-but-face-a-barrage-of-threats/"><![CDATA[<p>SectionsMore from Smithsonian magazineOur PartnersSubscribe to Smithsonian magazine and get a FREE tote.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Gabe Castro-Root
    
    
      
    
    A single Antarctic krill is about the size of your pinky finger. But with an estimated population of more than 700 trillion in the Southern Ocean, the tiny crustacean’s collective impact across the entire planet is enormous.Their swarms are so massive they can be seen from space. They’re food by the millions for seals and penguins and whales. And they sequester huge amounts of carbon—more than $15 billion worth per year, according to the World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF).Increasingly, though, Antarctic krill face threats from warming seas and a growing fishery. Scientists say that without international action to bolster marine protected areas and combat climate change, krill populations—and the resulting carbon sequestration—could drop off sharply in the coming decades.Antarctic krill act as one of the world’s largest “biological pumps,” a term scientists use to describe the process by which marine organisms send carbon to the depths of the ocean, where it can be stored for hundreds of years. A study published last September in Nature Communications found that Antarctic krill sequester similar amounts of carbon to coastal marshes, mangroves and seagrass, habitats scientists consider some of the planet’s most prolific carbon sinks.Krill feed on phytoplankton, which, like land-based plants, consume carbon dioxide and release oxygen as they photosynthesize. When krill waste sinks to the bottom of the ocean, all that carbon goes with it, essentially locking it away and freeing up space at the surface for more carbon to be absorbed from the air.“Krill are, by fact of life, living and molting and pooping and dying, and all that is very important to bring carbon from the surface ocean to the deep sea,” says Matthew Savoca, an ecologist at Stanford University. “When krill are doing that at the population level, they end up being an important ally in the climate change fight.”But Antarctic krill also face a host of challenges, including from warming oceans and an emboldened fishing industry, that researchers say require urgent attention. A study led by researchers at the British Antarctic Survey, published in Marine Pollution Bulletin this past December, found that an increase in plastic pollution in the Southern Ocean could inhibit krill’s ability to sequester carbon by 27 percent.While the sheer number of krill in the Southern Ocean means the species is unlikely to face an acute threat to its survival in the near term, Savoca is quick to point out that numbers are no guarantee of success.“You only have to look as far as our own country for the story of passenger pigeons to show you how quickly something can go from being incredibly abundant to extinct,” he says.The Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources, which regulates fishing activity in the Southern Ocean, failed at a meeting last October to renew a key measure aimed at preventing excessive krill harvests in any one area. The commission, which makes decisions by consensus among its 26 member states and the European Union, has been at a yearslong standstill over that measure and several proposed marine protected areas amid opposition from China and Russia.The result, says Zephyr Sylvester, an environmental researcher at the University of Colorado Boulder, is that fishing vessels are free to act on their companies’ directives until a new regulation is adopted. The lack of enforcement could allow the fishery to concentrate operations in a smaller area where it would have a larger environmental impact, she says.Krill are used in products ranging from nutritional supplements to livestock feed, and the WWF estimates the Antarctic krill fishery to be worth about $250 million annually.“We’ll learn a lot about the integrity of the fishery” now that the conservation measure has lapsed, Sylvester says, adding that external pressure, like the diplomatic and public awareness campaign in support of the Ross Sea Region Marine Protected Area a decade ago, remains among the most effective methods to turn scientists’ recommendations into policy. Still, she says, “it shouldn’t be the burden of consumers to enforce sustainable fishing practices.”At the same time, declining sea ice is exacerbating challenges for Antarctic krill from the earliest stages of life. Krill larvae don’t have the lipid reserves of adult krill to get through the dark Antarctic winter, says Hauke Flores, a marine biologist at the Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research in Bremerhaven, Germany. Instead, larvae stick to the sea ice, feeding on ice algae until the sun—and the phytoplankton—returns in spring.“Sea ice is critically important for Antarctic krill,” Flores says. “Without these algae that grow inside the sea ice, they will simply not survive.”The Antarctic Peninsula, which juts northward and where huge numbers of krill are concentrated, is warming five times faster than the global average, according to research backed by the National Science Foundation. As a result, scientists say, krill may be concentrating farther south in search of more stable sea ice. A 2023 study in Nature Reviews Earth &amp; Environment found that changes in the distribution of krill around Antarctica, driven by warming waters, threatened to increase interactions between fishing vessels and the animals that feed on krill, such as whales and penguins.The study’s lead author, So Kawaguchi, a krill ecologist at the Australian Antarctic Division, says scientists are still trying to understand exactly how climate change will affect Antarctic krill. From his lab in Tasmania, where he has a research aquarium filled with 20,000 krill, Kawaguchi has shown that, if carbon emissions remain unchecked, krill hatch rates in parts of the Southern Ocean could decrease by 70 percent within the next century.But he cautions that the effort to decode Antarctica’s shifting marine ecosystems is still in its early stages.“There are lots of other things we need to consider,” he says. “It’s just the start.”
        Gabe Castro-Root
        
        | Read More
      Email Powered by Salesforce Marketing Cloud (Privacy Notice / Terms &amp; Conditions)Follow UsExploreSubscriptionNewslettersAboutOur Partners
    © 2026 Smithsonian Magazine
  
      Privacy Statement [5/20/25]

  

  
  
      Cookie Policy [5/20/25]

  

  
  
      Terms of Use

  

  
  
      Advertising Notice

  

  
  
      Your Privacy Rights

  
Cookie Settings
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="krill"/><category term="media"/><category term="science-communication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The bountiful creatures sequester carbon and are a vital food source for marine predators, but their future is uncertain]]></summary></entry></feed>